Hey There YouTube um what do I think of
the book eloquent JavaScript is a
question I was given and it's kind of
fun that somebody asked this question um
even though we're not going to cover
JavaScript till later in the beginner
boost I want to say how much I love
eloquent JavaScript I always have um of
all the JavaScript books and believe me
I've studied all of them um this one is
my favorite it's my second favorite
actually there's another one honestly I
can't remember the name I'll put it in
the comments I haven't seen it so long
it was made by a french guy um it's just
very direct what are my criteria for
selecting a good JavaScript book first
of all let me just say my criteria are
not the same as somebody who is going to
be a
programmer by trade my choice of what
book is best is what book teaches the
fundamentals of programming and
particularly um you know the better
parts of JavaScript with getting into
its
warts um and I'm going to refrain from
commenting on all the other books out
there there are a couple books in
javascripts that that get me very angry
there's there's a couple that I
literally
hate I hate them they're so bad I'm not
gonna You're Gonna Want To Know You're
gonna have to come watch me you're gonna
have to ask me off the off the Record
officially so because I I'm not going to
throw it under the bus right now this
let's talk about what's good let's talk
about positive things things okie dokie
eloquent JavaScript is good because it
covers very basic things in a nice
organized way um and one of the things I
really love about it is that it
introduces you
to uh to functions but not just
functions to uh first class functions so
this is see this right here uh defining
a function right here this this is one
of the primary criteria for me on a
JavaScript thing um as you see here it
says a function definition is a regular
binding where the value of the binding
is a function and I got to just
say thank you thank you thank you thank
you thank you for writing this the right
way the reason this is so important is
because if you are teaching if you're
teaching a new person about programming
in general they learn about variables
they learn about data types they learned
you know basic data types like what's a
string what's a number this kind of
thing what's a letter and then when it
comes time to talk about
functions you know most books will you
know and other languages frankly will
dive into this kind of confusing side
quest that talks about well you have to
do this and this and this and but the
reason I like this so much is I'm going
to just I'm going to emphasize this
functions are just another data type
that is literally the meaning of a first
class function that means that functions
are just like any other data type they
can be assigned they can be changed they
can be reassigned they can be thrown
around they can be passed as arguments
they can be returned from a function and
if there's one thing that JavaScript
does really well and people are
surprised to hear this from me it's
dealing with first class functions and
functions you know and and frankly the
original idea behind objectoriented
programming which and I quote Jim
Copan allows the language to adapt to
the mental models of the user of the
programmer and class-based object Orient
programming such as languages like Java
and once again I quote Jim Cain one of
the agile Manifesto signers big time
deal you cannot code object Orient
programming in Java and I quote again
you have who here codes JavaScript he
said and you have a good chance of being
able to code true object Orient
programming the kind where you can adapt
part of the adaptation is allowing
functions to be reassigned at runtime
now some people will like cringe really
hard right there when I said that and we
could debate another day about whether
you should be able to change the
behavior of a program while it's running
but whether you agree with that or not
that is the definition the original
definition of objectoriented programming
go look it up so this is why I am such a
fan of el JavaScript because almost all
of the um JavaScript that we all all the
books that talk about JavaScript do not
do it this way now the only thing this
could do better that I would like it to
do better would have it to be a modern
version of this instead of having it be
the word function if it actually used
the modern uh JavaScript
notation which uh allows you to simulate
just you know greatly simplify this
using U this very functional syntax the
arrow function yeah it's absolutely
amazing and again this is another reason
that I really love JavaScript I love how
almost lispy I mean people call
JavaScript lisp all the time there's
people who regularly site that it is
really just Li lisp in
Disguise I don't know about that debate
if I would go so far as to say that um
but you see how this is constant here
that's because you can't change that
once it's been defined but if you were
to not have that be a constant then it
would be a dynamic behavior and it could
be swapped out you know the problem is
you'd have to make sure it was you know
synchronous but JavaScript is already
does everything if you're a beginner and
you're trying to decide what book to get
this is this is one of the best books to
get it's also free so um there are a
number of things that I don't like about
it
um I am kind of on the fence with regard
to
semicolons uh we will cover all of this
by the way when we do JavaScript we're
going to learn JavaScript and Python and
beginner boost at the same time and the
reason for that is because I want to
draw a really strong contrast between
the languages that are doing the same
thing two interpreted languages
interpreted means it's a little lucier
gooier and they were going to show you
because this right here you cannot you
can do something like this but you
cannot use anonymous functions in Python
in nearly the same way you can with they
have a thing called a Lambda but it's
not the same I promise you so why would
you care about that well that becomes an
issue related to what kind of languages
you want to use why you would use the
language uh this video is not about that
so this video is answering one question
should I use eloquent JavaScript to
learn JavaScript and my I think you
should I think it's a great idea um a
downside of this though is that this I
remember this does not have um a lot of
they have changed it since last time I
mean the last oh there's arop function
they edited what no way that was not
there when I first reviewed this
something like six years ago well back
at skill stack there's the arrow
function my friends isn't that gorgeous
oh I just love it I love the fat o
functions I just think they're so
gorgeous I wish go had it I really do um
but whatever uh you know I it's just
such a I I like JavaScript I
legitimately like JavaScript as the
syntax of JavaScript um there are a
couple of places that it gets a little
bit messy so for example semicolons um I
am I'm a fan of no semicolons but I
could be convinced to add them back um
if you're a beginner you should put them
in there because they're there but but
they can cause problems actually so you
don't have to have them but you should
have them because there's a few edge
cases I I have a I'll do a whole video
on that if I haven't done it already
whether it's just use semicolons or not
um but one of the downsides I was going
to tell you is that down at the bottom
here they don't there's not a lot of
projects um functions with side effects
a function with side effects is not a
function anymore at least it's not a
true function oh there we go a pure
function see this look it's telling you
about this stuff this is another reason
I love this it's actually getting in
what's the difference between a function
and a n this nobody talks about this
nobody talks about these very important
things that beginners need to know from
the very beginning no one no one talks
about this this so like you read you
read most books out there about
JavaScript they don't even touch that
topic so this is one of the reasons I
really like it uh feature I oh I don't
know about that I did not know about
that about the whole semicolon thing um
there are arguments both ways let's not
have that argument now
um there there is a problem if I
remember right with them not having uh I
remember there were a little light on
project
ideas um and they do talk about node.js
which you can't escape talking about
JavaScript without talking about
nodejs um and they also talk about the
Dom which is you know technically the
Dom is outside the scope of JavaScript
but since JavaScript was specifically
created to manipulate the Dom it's like
talking about C without talking about
Unix C was invented to create Unix
so JavaScript was invented to manipulate
the Dom therefore not talking about the
Dom in a book about JavaScript is kind
of you know would be wrong right so we
want we want to at least talk about the
document object model um does that put
this entire book into the sort of you
know underneath the web development uh
realm it kind of does but I mean let's
be real JavaScript is for web
development it is you can do all kinds
of other things with it but at the end
of the day JavaScript was created for
web development and it will continues to
be for web development and whatever form
and it's still primarily good at that
you know it's one of those don't cross
the streams things all right so so
that's it I guess that's kind of the end
I'm trying to see if there's anything
else here I forgot project a
robot um my favorite project by the way
if you're looking to do a pro this looks
pretty
cool um this is I don't remember this
project being there before was it always
there one of my favorite projects to do
in JavaScript is to make a an
interactive Story game um and I don't
know that we're going to be able to do
that we we might we might do that
actually that might be our major project
um and so yeah you're in the video
now um so so that is that's pretty much
it um an interactive Story game make a
story game where they can type in kind
of like zorc right the really great
thing about doing it with JavaScript is
you can actually put like jump scares
and Freddy Fazbear kind of
things into your so they can like be
thinking they're playing this text based
Adventure on their you know their
interactive text console in a web page
and all of a sudden you can like
surprise them with something it's really
fun um uh and so so yeah uh so that's my
that's that's my opinion on eloquent
JavaScript and we we'll make other
videos about if you have questions about
other things